Okay, let's talk about American identity
back in the colonial period and how that
developing identity started causing
conflicts with Big Mama Britain all the
way across the pond. So, if you're ready
to get them brain cows milked, let's get
to it. So, yeah, the fancy language to
describe what we're talking about is the
character of colonial society and
culture. Sorry, put my own self to sleep
there, but I'm here to tell you it's
much spicier than that. Really, what
we're talking about here is what makes
an American an American. And the short
answer, which I will presently him
explain, is diversity. And I know
throwing that word around in certain
circles is about as welcome as a fart in
an elevator, but let me explain. You
see, the 13 British colonies in America
contained arguably the most diverse
population in the world. And although
the majority of the population were
British, many other groups took up
residence in these colonies as well. For
example, German immigrants made up about
6% of the population, and in a lot of
cases, they left Germany on account of
religious persecution and economic
oppression. Many of them settled in
Pennsylvania and because they were
Lutheran Christians, they added to the
religious diversity of an already
diverse colonial population. And then
another group, the ScotsIrish, made up
about 7% of the population and many of
these folks settled on the Appalachian
frontier. Now, these happen to be land
Scots who were forced into Ireland by
Great Britain. And that's going to be
important in the next period because
they were emphatically not fans of
England. Anyway, the ScotsIrish also
brought with them their own Presbyterian
flavor of Christianity, which only
further diversified the population. And
then another 5% of the population
included other European immigrants, but
we're not going to get too far into the
weeds. And finally, about 20% of the
population was made up of enslaved
Africans. And as you may recall from
previous videos, they were mainly
concentrated in the south. And they
migrated not because they wanted to, but
because they were forced to. And then
another 5% of the black population
included free blacks who were mostly
concentrated in the upper south or
various urban areas. But free just means
that they weren't enslaved, not
necessarily that they enjoyed equal
rights with everyone else, because in
most cases, they very much did not. Oh,
and by the way, since we're here at the
end of a unit, you probably got a test
coming up, and you might want to check
out my A Push Heimler review guide,
which has everything you need to study
as fast as possible. It's got exclusive
whole unit review videos that you're not
going to see here on YouTube, note
guides to follow along, practice
multiple choice questions for each unit,
full-length practice exams, and answer
keys for every dang bit of it. So, if
that's the kind of help you need, then
get that clicky finger out and check the
link in the description. Anyway, all of
that to say, the American colonies were
home to a metric buttload of different
kinds of people. And that very diversity
in many ways became an important part of
the American identity in the colonies.
However, I'm not trying to imply that if
you walked up to some New England
British Puritans or some Pennsylvania
German Lutherans and asked, "What's an
American?" that they would say, "To be
an American is to be a diverse we." I
mean, just look at us. We're a big old
melting pot full of immigrants melted
into a single identity as Americans. Uh,
no. That's dumb and nobody thought that
way. In general, American identity was
still very much group based, and the
answer might change depending on which
group you were talking to. And to be
clear, these colonists didn't really
think of themselves as Americans, but
rather British subjects who happen to be
living in the geographical region of the
Americas. And speaking of which, here's
where I tell you that over the course of
this time period, the American colonies
were showing some signs of becoming more
British-like. Or if you're sassy, you
could say that the colonies were
experiencing a gradual Anglicization.
What I mean is by the end of this
period, colonial American society began
to look a lot more like British society
than ever. For example, a class of
merchants in the New England and Middle
colonies had become so rich that they
began to resemble the English nobility
in their customs and their dominance of
the social hierarchy. Their counterparts
in the south were a handful of elite
planters that were wealthy enough to own
many enslaved people and thus to
dominate local politics. Additionally,
increasing wealth in the colonies led to
a consumer revolution which led to an
increased demand for British goods,
especially among wealthier urban
families. And this meant that social
status was becoming less tied to birth
and family history and more to financial
success. Then as land grew scarce, more
and more people at the bottom of the
hierarchy became landless and poor. And
from where I sniff
that smells pretty British to me.
Additionally, by the end of this period,
all the colonies shared the same basic
government structure, which included a
governor and a legislative body divided
into two houses, which was the same
structure of government in England. Now,
to be clear, there were differences
between Britain and the American
colonies with respect to who appointed
those governors and the members of the
legislative bodies. The structure was
very British in nature, even if the more
local forms of government were more
American and representative in nature.
But here's where I tell you that there
were two movements that occurred in our
period that really did contribute to the
development of a more integrated
identity throughout the regions of the
colonies. And taken together, these
movements both contributed to and
further fostered the Anglicization that
I just talked about. Now, the first
movement that helped foster a more
holistic identity was the Enlightenment.
Now, by definition, the Enlightenment
was a European intellectual movement
that sought to apply the rigors of
scientific and philosophical reasoning
to society and politics. And part and
parcel of this movement was the emphasis
on rational thought and the rejection of
authority structures that came from
outside oneself, most notably religious
authority. And thanks to a robust
transatlantic print culture, the ideas
of the enlightenment crossed the
Atlantic and played a role in uniting
the colonists as a truly unique people.
For example, writers like John Lockach
and Jean Jacqu Rouso wrote about ideas
like natural rights and the social
contract. Both of which played a
significant role in the creation of an
American political philosophy. We'll
talk a lot more about those ideas in the
next unit, so I'll just leave it there
for now. And then the second movement
that helped foster a more holistic
identity was the Great Awakening which
occurred in the 1730s through the 1740s.
Now, in order for this to make sense,
you have to know that by the 1730s,
religion had generally declined in many
churches throughout the colonies. And if
you want an example, and I know that you
do, then let me tell you about the
halfway covenant. You remember how all
those New England Puritans were all,
"We're a city on a hill. We're going to
be God's beacon on earth." Yeah, they
were pretty intense about their
religion, and they only admitted people
into the church who could give a
credible testimony of their conversion.
But after about a generation, apparently
the younger folk weren't as interested
in the religious strictctures of their
parents. And that meant that they very
much could not meet the requirements for
church membership. And so the churches
began to get real sparse. And it was
that situation that led to the halfway
covenant, which allowed people to be
baptized even if they hadn't been
converted and thus became church
members. Now, they were still barred
from other ordinances like communion and
voting on church issues, but you know,
at least they were half Christians and
could still be part of the church.
Anyway, the point is religion was on the
decline, and that decline also had
political causes as well. You see, after
the glorious revolution in Great
Britain, the New England colonies were
forced to accept policies ensuring
religious tolerance, which, you know,
for the Puritans was kind of a bummer.
And that development only hastened the
decline of their particular
understanding of religion. But starting
in the 1730s, colonial religion came
roaring back to life in a massive
revival that swept through all the
colonies. It began in Massachusetts
under the preaching of a congregational
minister by the name of Jonathan
Edwards. And if you've ever heard of
him, it's probably because of his mildly
titled sermon, Sinners in the Hands of
an Angry God. And that might give you
the impression that Edwards was one of
those sweaty preachers who yelled at his
parishioners until the pulpit was
covered in flop sweat. But actually in
his preaching, he was pretty tame. And
although his sermons were tightly
reasoned and highly philosophical,
people began responding with highly
emotional outbursts which would become a
very big part of the American religious
identity. And that's essentially what a
religious revival was by Edward's
reckoning, an emotional response to the
preached word of God, which resulted in
the spontaneous conversions of large
numbers of people. And that's what the
Great Awakening was all about, reaching
the masses. Anyway, a few years later, a
British minister named George Whitfield
came to America and preached a similar
message, making prodigious use of his
famous and soaring oratory. He traveled
the continent, preaching in churches and
street corners and fields. And soon, a
religious fervor was lit in all the
colonies. And so, churches throughout
the colonies began following suit,
emphasizing personal, emotional,
religious experience. I mean, let's be
honest, could they even call themselves
Christians if they weren't shouting or
weeping or fervently chewing on a pew
rail? Uh, no. The answer is no. Anyway,
this growing emphasis on Christian
emotionalism led to a debate about
whether this kind of Christianity was
the real thing or merely an aberration.
On one side, you had the new light
clergy who believed that emotionalism
and personal experience with God
constituted the proper form of Christian
experience. But on the other side were
the old light preachers who were
skeptical of these kinds of religious
theatrics and pushed their people to a
more reasonable religion, which was
great for them because, you know, takes
some effort to get those teeth marks out
of the pew rails. Regardless, the point
is the Great Awakening spread rapidly
and it became the first mass movement in
the American colonies. And as such, it
helped form an identity among Americans
that helped them understand themselves
as a unique people. And just to tie all
the strands together, both the
Enlightenment and the Great Awakening
are movements that resulted from
Anglicization in the colonies. But
there's more than a little irony here.
The Enlightenment, not to mention the
Glorious Revolution, gave the colonists
a sense of pride in being British
subjects while at the same time
supplying them with the very ideas that
they would later use to challenge
Britain for the curtailment of their
rights as British citizens. And then the
revivalism of the Great Awakening
actually began back in England under the
leadership of folks like John Wesley. So
this very British movement spread
through the colonies, but at the same
time with its emphasis on personal
religious experience over against the
ordinances of the established Anglican
hierarchy, it gave the colonists a real
understanding of how to challenge
traditional authority. But even so,
American colonists often felt that they
were not merely the colonial slaves of
the British Empire, but something much
more unique and independent. And because
of that, tensions very much started
occurring between Big Mama Britain and
her colonies across the sea. And these
disagreements basically fall into three
big categories. First, colonists
disagreed with Great Britain regarding
territorial settlements in the Ohio
River Valley. So, on account of the
incredible colonial population increase
through natural reproduction and
immigration, land became real scarce in
the territories of the original colonial
boundaries. And so, many colonists
desired to push west into the Ohio River
Valley to create a better life for
themselves. But Great Britain was all
like, y'all so crazy. And that's because
colonist desire to migrate west created
two problems for Britain. First, they
wanted peace after so many bloody
conflicts with the indigenous peoples
who lived west of their colonial
territory. and allowing colonists to
claim further land would only reignite
those hostilities. Second, they feared
that by crowding French claims in the
region that it would spark a conflict
with them. And it very much did exactly
that. But I'll save that juicy story for
the next unit. Anyway, after considering
these problems, the British went ahead
and shut the idea for westward expansion
all the way down. And that, not
surprisingly, led colonists to get real
grumpy about their lot in life. Okay.
Now, the second category of disagreement
was regarding colonial self-ruule. Now,
remember from previous videos that
because of the big honking ocean that
separated the colonies from the imperial
mainland, the colonists developed their
own ways to rule themselves and had
gotten kind of used to making a lot of
their own decisions. And especially
during periods of salutary neglect when
Britain was distracted elsewhere with
more pressing issues, the colonists
could start to think that they were sort
of, you know, independent. But there
were other times when the British
government came back to remind the
colonists, "I'm your mama. Y'all do what
I say." And one particularly egregious
example of this was the practice of
impressment for the British Navy. So
long story short, Britain fought a
series of three wars concerning disputed
colonial borders. And because they were
always short of men in the British Navy,
the officers resorted to impressment to
fill their ranks. And that basically
means they forced colonial men to serve
in the war effort on British ships. And
everybody knew that living on a ship in
the navy meant that if the war didn't
kill you, then the dysentery probably
would. And that left those impressed
colonists uh real angry. And during one
of those wars, namely King George's war,
the resentment got so hot that it boiled
over into three days of rioting in
Boston in 1747. And while there's lots
of juicy stuff I could tell you about
those impressment riots, there's really
only one thing you need to stick into
your brain folds. These riots indicated
that colonists had developed a sense of
their natural rights and refused to
allow an imperial power to infringe on
those rights. Like technically speaking,
the colonists were British subjects and
Britain had every right to draft them
into their wars. But the fact that the
colonists were like, "Oh, heck no."
Tells you that in their own minds they
thought of themselves as perhaps more
than British subjects. And then one more
example of a conflict over self-ruule
during this period was the Zanger trial
of 1735. So, a guy named John Peter
Zanger ran a colonial newspaper in New
York, the goal of which was to inform
the public about British infringements
on colonial rights. And again, the
existence of this paper was owing to the
spread of the Enlightenment and the
growth of print culture that helped to
spread these ideas. And so, when he
published a piece criticizing the
dismissal of an American judge by the
corrupt Britishappointed governor of New
York, Zenger was hauled into court on
charges of sedition and liel. And at
that time, British liel laws didn't
distinguish between truth and falsehood,
only whether a published piece
undermined government authority, which
of course Zanger's piece very much did.
But even though Zanger had clearly
broken the law, as it was written, the
colonial jury acquitted him. And so this
trial represents yet another piece of
the growing resentment puzzle that was
being put together in the colonies
during this period. And finally, there
were disagreements between colonists and
Great Britain regarding trade. You see,
since the colonists were multiplying
like mad, that meant that they needed to
import increasing amounts of British
goods. But on the other side of the
ocean, the British population wasn't
really growing that much. So the demand
for American goods had kind of reached
its peak. But Americans were all kinds
of industrious and had metric buttloads
of goods to trade. However, if you'll
recall, through the Navigation Act,
Britain had restricted colonial trade to
Britain alone. And again, that ramped up
the colonial resentment because they
were forbidden to find other trading
partners for their growing stocks of
tradable goods. And so colonists found
ways to smuggle goods to buyers other
than Great Britain. A move which
bolstered their economy greatly. But
again, in time, the British would come
back and try to shut down all the
smuggling. And that would lead to yet
more resentment. And I bet that's going
to have some consequences in the next
unit. Okay, if you need help studying,
then click here to grab my A Push Himler
review guide or you can click here to
watch my other unit 2 videos. And I
appreciate you coming around and I'll
catch you on the flip-flop. I'm Lorett.